When the release of a
creative app gets announced,
...it's not something I get
particularly excited about,
...because I generally find
software announcements to be...
markety.
Full of hyper-positivity
and overpromise,
...which also kind of seems to
keep me at arm's length too,
...with claims to be "changing
the very concept of creativity",
..."enabling" my "wildest dreams",
...and "democratizing" bloody blah.
Thing is, though,
...since I spend most of my waking
life using creation software,
...I'm really interested
in how it gets made.
And since I work in
creative software,
...I know that, far from being dull,
...it's often a tenuous
and uncertain process,
...sometimes relates to its massive
disappointments in human drama.
For example, when I was a
...lead designer at Microsoft,
...I spent years working
on an app called Paint 3D.
Yeah, that's right.
That weird silly meme app?
I was there.
You'd assume we're all having
a blast making that, right?
[chuckles] Nope.
Paint 3D was forged in the fires of
...unexpected technical restrictions,
...never-ending external pressures,
...including an internet uprising
when people found out that
...it was intended to replace
the original MS Paint on Windows,
...along with continued disagreement
about its overall purpose.
On the other hand, there
was an enormous amount of
...technical and creative skill
involved in its creation too.
So, all in all,
...a very memorable production
...that I'd love to
delve into but can't,
...because I signed a piece of
paper that allows Microsoft to
...torpedo my house if I
ever divulged state secrets.
And now it's being
used to make NFTs.
Um... [sighs] Wha-
[exasperated sigh]
Why i- Why is life like this?
So when a new version of
a creative app is released,
...my questions are nearly always,
"What were the compromises here?"
"What didn't work out?"
"What were the emergencies
and changes of plan?"
And when it's
particularly successful,
...what I want to know is,
"How is it done?"
"What magic combination of organization
skill and good luck made this possible?"
So that's the idea behind this video.
Since I've been lucky enough
to find myself in a position
...where I'm leading one of
the major composition apps,
...Musescore,
...I'm going to describe
the gigantic effort
...that went into the release
of our latest version:
This was the most massive release
...of anything I've ever worked on,
...which took a very taxing
and physically exhausting
...two-and-a-half years to complete.
Mercifully, it wasn't
a troubled production,
...just an incredibly long one.
So, in this video, I'm
going to talk about
...how we redesigned its look,
...made big changes to its usability,
...how we overhauled the notation
...and how we overhauled
the playback too.
And although I've made this
video for a general audience,
...Musescore users will
most likely enjoy it too.
Even if it's just so
you know who to blame
...for moving the concert-pitch
toggle down here,
...next to the 'Subscribe' button
...and the 'Quit Sibelius' button,
...the 'New All' button,
...the Eye of Terpsichore,
...the pop-up switch, and
...the Pro-Level Chords generator,
...although- Actually,
...actually, hold on.
None of these work until you-
you flick the switch over he-
[noises of portal materialising]
[giggles]
"My name's Jankman!"
"Ah, it looks like you're
trying to write a symphony."
"Would you like help with that?"
"O- Oh, wait, it's-"
"It's for solo piano."
"My- My mistake!"
"I'll see myself out."
Jesus, Jankman!
Oh, god...
Jankman, what have you done!?
Oh, no.
How am I-
How am I supposed to talk
about Musescore without you?
Oh...
...the walls are closing in...
CAT!
CAT! CAT!
CAT! CAT! CAT!
Let me start by quickly describing
...the state of affairs with
Musescore before I arrived.
First of all, if you don't know,
...Musescore is an
open-source project
...that was created by a
community of unpaid contributors.
The leaders of the project
at the time were:
Werner Schweer,
Thomas Bonte,
...and Nicolas Froment.
And the more I learn about
these guys and talk to them,
...the more I'm blown away by
what they managed to achieve.
You'll see why in a second.
So, before my team of full-time
professionals joined the project,
...I want to describe how the
community builds Musescore 3.
To begin with, Werner the founder
...began working on an overhaul
to the notation system,
...which would take it far beyond
the capabilities of Musescore 2.
It took years of work,
but eventually
...when he had the
main systems in place,
...he then opened it up
to the community,
...who set about
polishing and refining
...every other aspect of the app,
...using chat rooms and forums
to hash out the details.
Different contributors would volunteer
...to take on parts of
the remaining work,
...and would submit their
progress piece-by-piece
...to the whole group for review.
It would then be up to
Werner or Nicolas,
...the heads of the project,
...to accept or reject each submission.
In the open-source world,
...most contributions tend
to be small contained tweaks
...rather than large overhauls.
This is practical, because
...small changes are less likely
to impact on someone else's work,
...which makes them much
more likely to get accepted.
This also suits the routines
of open-source contributors
...whose involvement is
almost always part-time.
But with the community as
vibrant as Musescore's,
...there were loads of people
willing to take part.
So, eventually,
...all these thousands of little
fixes and suggestions came together
...after enormous amounts
of testing and revision,
...until a new stable
release was ready.
I've seen this process
many times myself,
...and it's a beautiful
thing to watch.
However, as powerful
as the system is,
...it does come with
one major drawback:
A mountain of architectural instability.
I can best explain this using
the metaphor of city planning.
Musescore was
...less a Singapore and
...more of a Houston.
A free-for-all, where,
...in order to build anything,
...you have to do your best to
...plug into whatever existing
...uncoordinated and
inefficient structures
...you find yourself sitting on top of.
By the time we got to the end
of development on Musescore 3,
...which I spent a lot
of time working on,
...it was an amazingly
complex potpourri
...of thousands of
patchwork improvements
...that depended upon and reinforced
...other patchwork improvements,
...all hanging together
through a combination of
...workarounds,
...inefficient additional processes,
...and straight-up hacks.
A massive technical debt,
...which, practically speaking, meant
...that if you tried to
make a change to one thing,
...you'd break seven other
unrelated things in the process.
And this is not a criticism of the
Musescore community, by the way.
Far from it, actually.
This structural problem
is almost unavoidable
...and inherent to many
open-source applications,
...which often can't afford full-time
developers to manage code quality
...alongside experienced designers
who can plan years in advance.
Although it's not like professional companies
...regularly get this right either.
Spaghetti code seems to
be the norm everywhere.
Like, I remember once while
working on Paint 3D,
...I asked a developer to
change the color of a button
...from orange to blue.
And when he did this,
...the orange option in
the main color palette
(that's the thing you
used to paint with)
...also became blue,
...giving users four
blues and no oranges.
Anyway, if we ever wanted
to be able to move quickly,
...we had to take a step back
in order to take two forward.
And that really was
the main purpose of
...the first year of
Musescore 4 development:
Build ourselves the right
technical underpinning
...before proceeding with
major improvements.
However, we had one big problem.
Since the level of core
work was so massive,
...to the point where it
would be unreasonable
...to expect our community
to take it on,
...we needed to beef up
our internal team,
...which at that point
consisted of two people:
myself
...and our fresh new
developer, Vasily.
So step one was to find
and hire a new team.
And, by the way, trying to find
designers, developers, and testers
...who all have
experience with notation
...is like trying to find a dog
with a degree in criminology.
So, Vasily and I
started calling friends
...and doing everything we could
think of to spread the word.
Since London was both a hub
for classical music and design,
...I was looking into setting
up a new office there.
It was actually all getting
really exciting at that point.
We were finally on our way.
Finally hitting the ground.
['Inception' bwaaam]
Okay, so the pandemic was something that
...caused enough trouble to all our lives,
...so I won't delve into
my own experiences here.
Suffice it to say that the
London office idea was scrapped,
...and eventually we decided to
become a fully remote team instead.
Because of the general nastiness
of this whole period,
...we definitely felt like we were being
battered from pillar to post for a while.
But as we adjusted, we realized
...that there was one
gigantic silver lining.
Because we were now fully remote,
...we could hire expertise
from anywhere in the world.
And even though it
took almost two years
...until we had a fully
rounded team in place,
...this was actually a
critical turning point for us.
Vasily built the
core development team
...by bringing in three people
he'd worked with before.
As for me, looking for designers,
engraving experts, and testers,
...I spent a lot of time
scrolling through portfolios,
...looking through LinkedIn profiles,
and interviewing candidates.
My social media following turned
out to be a real blessing here,
...since, apart from finding people
...by posting openings
on Twitter and YouTube,
...a few people actually found me.
I'll introduce everyone as
we go through this video.
So, one little note before we continue,
...to help you easily distinguish
between Musescore 3 and Musescore 4,
...which I'm going to be
comparing quite a lot,
...version 3 will always
be using the light theme,
...and version 4 the dark theme.
So, now that I've discussed the
need to re-architect Musescore,
...let me describe the
situation on the design side.
Musescore 3 was largely
constructed from
...a set of UI components called:
Now, Qt Widgets are what
...we often refer to
in music tech as
...a pain in the arse,
...because when trying to
construct an interface,
...they're quite limited
...and often require
disappointing compromise.
We learned this the hard way
building features in Musescore 3.
For example,
...one of my first ever designs
...specify the need for
pop-ups that work like this.
Well, Qt Widgets said, "No,"
...so we decided to
recreate this entire panel
...using the interface
language QML instead.
And since that experiment
worked really well,
...when planning Musescore 4,
we decided to
...remove our dependence
on Qt Widgets completely
...and remake the entire
interface using QML.
And this was no small
decision, by the way.
It meant that every single
interactive and visual element
...had to be rebuilt from scratch.
Buttons,
...scroll bars,
...tabs,
...drop-downs,
...sliders,
...more buttons,
...context menus,
...modal dialogs,
...non-modal dialogs,
...pop-ups,
...search boxes,
...spin boxes,
...grips,
...check-boxes,
...et cetera.
And on top of that,
...colour styles,
...text styles,
...about 400 icons,
...rollover states,
...disabled states.
As well as all the
accessibility features
...like focus states
...and screen reader support
...that gets built
on top of that too.
And all of it had to work on
...MacOS,
...Linux,
...and PC.
Starting at UI from
scratch like this
...is a dangerous step to take,
...and I would usually
recommend not doing it
...unless you have the right
experience on your team.
But, that said, once we've built it,
...it was a dream
compared to Qt Widgets.
A way more flexible and capable system
...that allowed us to move so
much more speedily than before.
And, by the way, since this
component library is open-source,
...we encourage any
other apps to use it.
For example, we're
planning on reusing it
...for the remake of
the Audacity interface.
So, to help me handle
all of this UI work,
...I eventually found
...Jessica, a visual designer
...who also has a music
production background.
Musescore was actually
her first ever design job,
...but despite that,
...it only took about a year
until she had taken over
...virtually all my UI
design responsibilities.
For anyone who likes our
new mixer, by the way,
...that's just one example
of Jessica's work.
Now, apart from that,
...remaking the UI also gave
us the golden opportunity
...to go back over the
experience of the app
...and make it more intuitive,
...rooting out as many frustrating
and bizarre elements as possible.
But we were careful
not to go too far,
...because there is a lot of
stuff that Musescore gets right.
And throughout the redesign,
...I spent a lot of
time talking to users
...to find out what they
liked and didn't like.
And a massive thanks to everyone who
...responded to my posts on Twitter
over the years, by the way.
There were so many little things
that changed or didn't change
...as a result of your feedback.
Another really invaluable
source of advice
...came from our community
of contributors,
...many of whom have been
around a lot longer than me.
They provided a lot of context
...so we understood how and
why certain features were built.
Let's start with the most
important control in the app:
the note input bar.
This was something that
already worked quite well
...and just needed
a few improvements.
For example, it felt obvious that
...we should add articulations
and tuplets here,
...because they're so often needed
...they really should just
be considered primary controls.
We also made this bar much
easier to customize too,
...so if there's something you
want or don't want to see here,
...you can access this pop-up
to turn them on or off
...or rearrange their order.
This is one of those tweaks
that lets us scale in future too,
...so when we want to add
potentially useful options
...like this one for
cross-staff beaming,
...we can do so without worrying
too much about clutter.
Let the user choose what
they want and don't want.
And there was a lot of redundancy
and duplication to address too,
...which is partly a
result of years of
...features being built
upon other features.
For example, there were
...two different play
panels in Musescore 3
...that contained a lot
of the same stuff
...but with each having
something unique about it.
We combined these two panels into one
...and kept it close to where the
primary play controls were before.
There were also two different panels
...for entering and editing text,
...which again duplicated
loads of functionality,
...producing loads of unresolved bugs.
Like, if you made text bold down here,
...this panel didn't
seem to recognize it,
...so if you toggled on or off bold,
...it just didn't work.
In testing, this lower panel
performed really poorly too,
...mainly because users
just didn't see it.
So we also combined these panels
...and got rid of all the weird bugs.
When it came to the mixer,
...the Musescore 3 version
was big and weird-looking
...and didn't dock anywhere
that was comfortable.
For version 4,
...we placed it at
the bottom of the app
...with a little toggle up here that
lets you quickly switch it on and off.
We made so many other
changes like this
...it would take hours to go through.
Instead,
...to give a general sense
of how we approached the redesign,
...I'm going to focus on
just two examples in detail.
When it comes to software design,
...I am not a fan of things like
...a priori rules or design mantras
...that are always considered
to be true no matter what.
I'm much more in favor of
adaptability in real-world testing.
But with that said,
...there is one rule I tend to
stick to in designing software,
...which is to always focus on
the experience of a new user.
The reason for this is
that if a new user can
...figure out how your app works
without needing a tutorial,
...it creates a
baseline of simplicity
...that really benefits
everyone in the long run.
It's the hardest possible
measure of success,
...which is why I
tend to focus on it.
Let's take the experience of
setting up a score for the first time.
This is our handshake with new users.
In Musescore 3, setting up a score
...was already pretty good,
...but there were plenty of annoyances
that I wanted to get rid of.
Let me show you.
So, when you first go
to 'File' > 'New...',
...you're taken to a dialog
called the 'New Score Wizard'.
When opened, it asks you to specify
...what the title of your
score is going to be,
...along with some
other information like
...the name of the composer or arranger,
...and also some copyright information.
Now, on paper, it makes
sense to start like this,
...but it's not all always the case that
you begin a score with a title in mind.
So, let's leave this blank
for now and 'Continue'.
Next, you're taken to this page,
...which in testing
...always causes new users
to do a double-take.
'Choose Instruments'?
'Treble Clef'?
'Bass Clef'?
'Great Stave'?
What?
And why is this image
over here blank?
Well, what's going on
...is that all these options,
apart from the first one,
...are score templates.
If you select one,
...the image on the right shows you
what that template will look like.
So this first option
'Choose Instruments'
...is actually a way of
bypassing the templates page.
So, if you select it
and press 'Continue',
...you're then taken to
the section where you can
...manually add whatever
instruments you want instead.
Okay, so let's stop for a moment
...to look at this poll
I published on Twitter:
Now, as you can see here,
...a significant majority of users
...prefer to add their
instruments manually,
...despite the fact that templates
are offered to them first.
In other words, for most people,
...this is the most important
part of the New Score Wizard.
Aside from that,
...look at all this detail
here on the the right.
It's quite dense.
You see the instruments,
...but also the number of
staves for each instrument too.
And if we look closer,
there's some odd stuff.
For example, these piano staves here
...have strangely
titled options like
'Custom Standard'
...and 'Custom Percussion'.
Trying to explain why these
are here would take forever.
Suffice it to say,
they don't do anything.
All in all, this panel is just
...overly noisy and complicated.
Anyway, after you've
selected your instruments,
...there are two more
pages to get through.
Choose the key signature,
'Continue'.
Choose the time signature,
...pickup measures,
...number of bars,
...and tempo,
...and then you're finally done.
And your score appears great.
And one thing to note here is that,
...since we chose not to fill in the
title and composer fields earlier,
...the top of the score is now blank.
Makes sense.
We made our bed, so
...now we have to
sleep in it, right?
Well, sure, but
...if you eventually do want
to add this information later,
...it's not exactly easy
to discover how to do that,
...since they're up in
the main menu here,
...which many people never figure out.
In fact, many users
don't realize that
...titles are a unique
type of text object
...and just add regular
text here like this,
...which causes even more problems
with part scores down the road.
Now, individually,
...none of these issues have
just talked about are critical,
...but they really do add up to
...confusion for first-time users
...and persistent annoyances
for experienced users.
So here's what we did
in Musescore 4 instead.
When you press 'New',
...you're taken straight to the section
where you define your instruments.
And if you prefer templates,
...there's a tab right here that
lets you choose them instead.
And since Musescore will now
remember which tab you chose,
...the next time you create a score,
...it maximizes the
likelihood that you'll see
...the options most relevant to you.
Now, if you choose to
manually add instruments,
...you'll notice the
interface is much simpler.
We also added little descriptions
for each instrument down here
...to give those who are just
starting out some helpful guidance.
Once you've added your instruments,
...you can just press 'Done'.
Or you can press 'Next',
...which takes you to a
final page that combines
...these three pages
from Musescore 3:
We achieved this by using pop-ups,
...which minimise cognitive load
...by only displaying
info you want to see.
All in all, when comparing
version 3 to version 4,
...the maximum number of steps
has been reduced from five to two.
However we're not quite
finished, because
...when your score is then created,
...if you had earlier chosen
not to fill in these fields
...for title, composer, et cetera,
...Musescore now adds these
default titles automatically
...so you can fill them in
whenever it's convenient
...or just delete them.
Probably the most
significant change we made
...was to how part scores
can be viewed and edited.
In Musescore 3, to see your parts,
...you needed to open
this 'Parts' dialog
...hidden away in the file menu,
...then, faced with this
whole load of blank,
...you need to figure out
to press this button
'All Parts',
(formerly:)
...which generates your part scores,
...that then appear here as tabs
...that can't ever be closed.
Now, if you want to
modify these parts,
...this is where I need to
issue a headache warning.
Right.
Say you're writing a piano trio
...and the violin
player asks you to
...include the piano
in their part score.
So, the process for doing this is...
It's...
[sighs] Okay.
Press 'All Parts',
...and then click the file in here.
Right.
Then go down here where you can see
'Instruments in Part'.
So, if I now click on this piano
...and press this 'plus' button,
...a piano is added to
this box on the right,
...which means that the
violin part now has
...both the violin
and the piano in it.
Great! We're done.
Oh, hold on.
I just realised.
I actually wanted the piano
to be above the violin.
Damn.
Okay, let's open this
back up again, except
...now the part is locked,
...because once it's been generated,
...that's it. You can't change it.
Right, so we need to
delete this part entirely
...and create a new one
by pressing 'Single Part'.
Okay.
Now let's add the piano first,
...and then the violin,
...and finally we have
the arrangement we wanted.
Can you now see why so many users
...didn't know this was possible?
Now, over to Musescore 4.
Where to begin?
I need to introduce Roman,
...one of our developers
who built a ton of features
...over the last
two-and-a-half-years,
...including an improvement to
the performance of part scores,
...which in turn freed us up to
design a simplified experience.
First, we put a prominent
'Parts' button here.
Using this, you can open your parts
...and close them again
whenever you want.
Then, using this new
'Instruments' panel,
...you can now quickly
include or exclude
...whatever instruments you
want in your part scores
...and rearrange them at any time too.
In this way, changes you make
are instantly visible on the score,
...rather than an abstraction
in a mad-looking dialog.
The really fun part of the design
process was working on the UI.
In particular, the colours,
...which Jessica and I spent
a lot of time figuring out.
We began by establishing
...twelve colour definitions,
...each one filling a
particular purpose.
The colour of backgrounds,
...the colour used for text,
...the colour for buttons,
...et cetera.
Our rule was that everything in the app
...had to use one of these definitions.
Now, the trick to the
definitions is that
...they can change their
colour depending on the context.
If the app is using the light theme,
...the button colour is this:
If it's using the dark theme, this:
This means that when
we design something,
...all we have to do is create
it using the light theme,
...and the dark theme comes for free.
We also created one
special colour definition
...called 'ACCENT_COLOUR',
...which allowed us to provide
...theming options for
people to choose from.
And the other reason we built
this system was accessibility.
In particular, a customizable
high-contrast mode
...for users with various different
kinds of visual impairment
...like low-vision,
...poor-contrast perception
...or colorblindness.
This particular design
was implemented by
...a community member
called Arjun Tunasia.
Thanks, Arjun!
Actually, it is worth
deviating from the UI
...just to talk about
accessibility for a moment.
I worked a lot on accessible
design while at Microsoft,
...and when I came to Musescore,
...found a kindred spirit in
our community member Peter,
...who had done a lot of
accessibility work in Musescore 3
...and who later on joined
our internal team too.
Together, we designed a new
system for keyboard navigation
...which, along with our
expanded screen reader support
...and ability to export in Braille,
...makes Musescore 4 much more
accessible for blind users
...compared to version 3.
And it's worth mentioning that
much of this was made possible
...due to the massive work
done under the hood
...by our architect Igor.
Igor works in the shadows
...on the continuous
de-Houstonification of Musescore.
He's one of the reasons we've been
able to build as much as we have.
Anyway, back to the interface.
All the changes we made amounted to
...thousands of pages
of design specs,
...but design is only halfway there.
All this stuff needed to be built,
...and two developers
in particular had to
...take on the majority of that work.
I've already introduced you to Roman,
...but have not yet
introduced Elnur,
...who is responsible for a lot of the
accessibility work I've just described.
The effort these guys put into
building this entire interface
...was really incredible.
No matter how many times I tested
their work and suggested improvements,
...they just took it on the chin,
...sending me revision after revision
...until the feature
in question was solid.
The community provided a ton of
help on polishing the interface too.
In particular, there are
three people who pumped
...endless hours into the project.
The first is Casper,
...who worked seemingly non-stop
...while preparing for his
first year in university.
He has since joined
our internal team too.
Another two notable
contributors to the interface
...are Hemant Anthony
...and Dylan Nicholson.
Users owe these guys a big thanks.
There are of course many
other community members
...who contributed in a big way
to areas outside of the interface,
...but there are simply
too many to mention here,
...so if you want to know
who to say 'thank you' to,
...you'll see their names
in the credits at the end.
When we were at the
early planning stages,
...one of our main goals
was to modernize
...Musescore's playback capability
...by supporting VST instruments.
Now, VST is obviously
fantastic for DAWs
...like Ableton or Logic.
If you have an orchestral VST,
...you can, with enough tweaking,
...achieve some very
realistic-sounding results.
However, from the point of
view of a notation app,
...orchestral VSTs are
extremely awkward to work with,
...and tend to provide,
with one exception,
...quite poor results.
...and I think it's
worth explaining why.
First, let me describe the
goal for any notation app.
When a user plugs in a
library of orchestral sounds,
...it should just work immediately.
Violins should sound like violins,
...and performance techniques like
...pizzicato, arco, or tremolo
...should just sound
like those things.
The user shouldn't have
to manually hook it all up.
But at present,
...bearing in mind that
one exception I mentioned,
...this doesn't happen.
No matter how expensive
the orchestral VST,
...it will not automatically know
...what sounds to play
in a notation app.
The reason for this is MIDI,
...the protocol used by notation apps
...to send musical instructions to VSTs.
MIDI has no understanding
of notation at all,
...because it wasn't
designed for that purpose.
Take this notated example.
We have four notes within a slur.
Each note has a staccato mark,
...and the fourth note
has an accent too.
This is followed by a tremolo
direction in the next bar.
Now, since MIDI has no understanding
of any of these concepts,
...notation apps have to
provide a translation
...that tells MIDI what
instructions to send to a VST,
...but that translation is lossy,
...discarding a ton of vital
information along the way.
To play this example,
...here's what MIDI will send to a VST.
First, the pitches of each note.
That part's fine.
However, for the duration of each note,
...bearing in mind
these staccato marks,
...that's where things get messy.
All MIDI can send in
this instance are:
...and:
...events,
...which basically means,
"Start the note now."
"End the note now."
So even if the VST has a specific
recording of a staccato sound,
...it has no idea that staccato
has been specified on the score.
All it knows is the instruction
'start now'
...and then another instruction
a fraction of a second later
'end now'.
It doesn't know when the 'end now'
instruction will be called,
...so it can't even take an educated
guess at what the intention is.
It's like placing a screen
in front of a performer
...that only gives
moment-to-moment instructions.
"Okay."
The player would have no
idea what's coming next,
...so would not be able to provide
any kind of musical interpretation.
Back to the notation again.
To represent this accent,
...MIDI will usually send
a higher velocity
...compared to the other notes,
...so that it sounds louder.
If it has a specific
recording of a staccato accent,
...it doesn't know to use it.
It just plays whatever its
default is for that velocity:
And this tremolo,
...which is meant to sound like this:
God, that's where
desperation sets in.
Basically all you can do is specify
...a quick succession of
'note on' and 'note off' events,
...which results in this
grim-sounding machine-gun effect:
The only way VSTs can
perform more accurately
...is if notation apps provide
dedicated support for them.
The problem with this
...is that there's also no
standardization among VST instruments,
...even ones from the
same manufacturer.
This means that dedicated support
...needs to be provided on
a plug-in-by-plug-in basis.
An enormous burden for notation apps,
...which is why it
generally doesn't get done.
And the problem gets passed
to the user instead,
...who needs to be
technically savvy enough to
...map sounds themselves by manually
...associating all kinds of abstract
MIDI parameters with notated symbols.
It's a slow and, for most,
...bafflingly complicated process.
But even if you do know how to hook up
a notation app with an orchestral VST,
...there's another severe limitation,
...which is that VST
is a real-time format.
This takes us back to that example of
putting a screen in front of a performer
...that prevents them from
seeing what's coming next.
All MIDI can do is give
...immediate moment-to-moment
instructions to a VST,
...and can't look ahead to
provide vital Information like
...when a phrase is going to end.
If it could,
...VST developers would
be free to create
...all kinds of clever systems that
can provide a musical interpretation,
...including a meaningful
application of machine learning.
But because they don't
know what's coming next,
...they can't interpret context.
This limitation is really
holding orchestral VSTs back
...in terms of what they can offer,
...which is why even the most
expensive VST libraries you can buy
...sound pretty underwhelming
and machine-like in notation apps.
The only way a user
could get around this
...was to buy the VST NotePerformer,
...which sidesteps the
limitations of MIDI and VST
...by working directly with
notation apps like Sibelius,
...who provided dedicated
support for it.
This allows them to send mutually
agreed-upon musical instructions,
...so NotePerformer understands
the notated context.
And to sidestep the real-time problem,
...they came up with a clever hack,
...which was to intentionally
delay playback
...for around a second after
you press the play button,
...so that it has enough lead time
to know what's coming next
...and calculate a
musical interpretation.
NotePerformer is great,
...but it's a solution
that can't scale.
The burden and risk
of having to provide
...dedicated support to
multiple notation apps
...and receive dedicated support
from each of them in return
...is just too hard
for others who might
...otherwise be tempted
to enter into the market.
That's why there's only one option:
NotePerformer,
...even though there are hundreds
of sample libraries out there
...that were recorded at
the highest possible level.
It's insane when you think about it.
Why doesn't EastWest Quantum Leap
...naturally integrate with Sibelius?
The answer?
The limitations of MIDI and VST.
It's a very unsatisfying
state of affairs,
...but really all we could
hope for with Musescore 4
...without developing new
standards of our own.
So our initial plan was to
at least reach the standard,
...and then figure out how to
go beyond it in later releases.
So we buckled down,
...feeling quite satisfied that
we had a solid path forward.
It's just good to feel secure
...in knowing where you're-
['Inception' bwaaam]
['Incepti-]
['Ince-]
['I-]
['I']
TRAPPED IN CAPTIONING STUDIO
SEND HELP
Okay, we return back to MIDI
and VST in just a second,
...but I first need to
describe what happened.
...when Muse was joined by Audacity,
...the famous open-source
audio editor,
...and StaffPad,
...a notation app for tablet.
First, to my surprise,
...I was asked to also
lead the Audacity project,
...which involved hiring a
new team and setting out
...an entirely new and very
different development roadmap.
This required a big
change to how I worked,
...because until then,
...I was wearing quite a few
hats on the Musescore team,
...being the lead on the project
...but also the senior designer
and the main tester all in one.
And since that was obviously
no longer going to be possible,
...it meant that I needed to
find more people to take on
...many of my old responsibilities.
And it was around this moment
...that I was contacted
by a guy called Bradley,
...who had seen a video I released
about a new notation font last year.
As luck would have it,
...he was a perfect
addition to the team,
...being a UX designer who also
has a PhD in Musical Performance.
Brad is the criminology dog.
And even though he came on board
a little later in the project,
...his impact was massive.
Now, as for the StaffPad acquisition,
...this changed things in a very
different way because it brought
...a lot of playback and orchestral
recording know-how into our orbit.
And as we got to know
the StaffPad team,
...we began formulating plans to
develop a playback system of our own
...that was based on notation,
...including the ability to send
score information in advance,
...something that would open us
up to all kinds of possibilities
...with creators of orchestral
sounds in the future.
But we needed a first showcase of
...the kind of playback that
was going to be possible
...given all this new rich information
being sent from Musescore.
So, the StaffPad team began recording
...an entirely new set
of orchestral sounds
...as well as a new
sampler technology,
...all of which would
eventually become
...an external plugin that
worked with Musescore.
However, we still had to face
the massive obstacle of time.
Because it was important that
Musescore still worked with VST,
...we had to develop a
system that could support
...real-time formats via MIDI
...as well as non-real-time
formats via notation,
...something that's
never been done before.
And for that reason, we knew that
this was going to take a while.
We felt it would most likely
become a Musescore 5 thing.
And just as we were
coming to this conclusion,
...I got a curious email
from Eugenie Nadianov,
...the founder of the company:
Now, I didn't quite know how
to respond to this right away.
I loved the idea.
I really wanted to do it,
...but suspected the
time extension required
...would take the option
off the table for version 4.
So I wrote:
And I followed that with the list
of all the challenges involved,
...along with the dreaded
time estimates too.
I remember feeling a little
down while writing this,
...because I honestly thought it would
be considered out of the question.
But the response I got was:
It was one of the most surprising
...and enormously consequential
moments of my career,
...and of course I wasn't gonna
argue, because it meant that
...Musescore 4 wouldn't just be
a big step in the right direction,
...it would be the most significant
update to a notation app ever.
Now, since there is no universal
standard out there that we could use,
...we had to develop this
playback system from scratch,
...and there were many
unknowns involved.
This is where our good
looks struck again,
...because it turned out
that early developer Vasily,
...who I've already introduced,
...was no ordinary developer.
He had been advocating for a while that
...we needed to develop
our own solution,
...and once we got the go-ahead,
...built over the course of two years
...with the weight of the
entire project on his shoulders
...the playback system
we needed in its entirety.
First, it sends rich notated context.
Second, it can continuously
process a score
...and send it to a
sampler in advance,
...which enables the sampler to
calculate a musical performance.
And it hasn't dropped any
MIDI compatibility either,
...so things like external keyboards,
...soundfonts, and VSTs
all work perfectly.
Watching this mountain of work
come together was astonishing,
...although I have to admit
...the testing was a nightmare,
...reviewing hundreds of different
combinations of techniques
...played by hundreds of
different instruments
...across a variety of tempos,
...using a gazillion different scores.
It was endless,
...but ultimately worth it,
...because once we combined our playback
system with the orchestral plugin,
...which we eventually gave the name:
...the improvement in
quality was insane.
Let me demonstrate by comparing
it to the playback of version 3.
I hope you agree
...the time extension was worth it.
So, now that our timeline
had been extended,
...our engraving expert Simon
(you remember Simon, right?)
...and his team were able to achieve
...far more significant changes
than we'd originally planned.
First, I should explain the
overall purpose of these changes.
The primary focus of engraving
is to achieve two things:
the highest possible legibility
...and the highest possible beauty.
And these aren't separate goals,
...because it tends to be the
case that an improvement in one
...naturally leads to an
improvement in the other.
For example, spacing.
When symbols are too close together,
...it can confuse the eye
and look unpleasant.
When they're too far apart,
...the negative space
becomes distracting
...and the eye can be tricked
into making associations
...between elements that have
nothing to do with each other,
...which can often lead to
mistakes in musical performance.
So, in all cases, you need
to find the perfect balance
...which naturally synthesizes
beauty and legibility.
In pursuit of this goal,
...one key issue to avoid is noise.
Take this example,
...where, due to
imprecise positioning,
...all kinds of unintentional
collisions are occurring,
...which makes the symbols
harder to identify
...while also creating
loads of extra shapes
...which contributes
noise to each bar,
...making the whole
more difficult to read.
I often think about
these noisy objects
...as things that the
eye can get caught on,
...like a snag.
But since there are nearly
always too many symbols
...and not enough space
to achieve the ideal,
...excellent engraving
is really all about
...choosing the best
possible compromise.
As you add more and more information,
...the score must
continuously rebalance
...to maintain the
best possible spacing
...while avoiding as many
eye snags as possible.
I can't begin to describe how
many thousands of variables
...need to be written
to achieve this,
...and how much testing
it takes to get right.
Our ambitions for Musescore 4
...necessitated a rewrite
of a significant amount
...of the existing engraving code.
One of the biggest rewrites was
...to how slurs and
ties look and behave.
To demonstrate,
...let's look at these
chords in Musescore 3.
If we now tie these together,
...you'll see loads of collisions,
...as if the chords are
conducting missile warfare.
Ties are going through notes.
They're crisscrossing over each other.
This tie down here on the A is okay,
...but it's colliding with
the lowest stave line,
...with the ends of either side
only barely poking through.
In this case, it is legible,
...but just a bit ugly.
However, these same features produce
...much more of a
problem here on the C.
Because this tie is also
touching a stave line,
...it's harder to make out
the overall arc.
And because you can't make out
...where either end of
the tie terminates,
...the overall object
is tough to read,
...and much, much tougher
at normal sizes.
But we're not done yet.
Let's add some augmentation dots,
...and now you can see that
the ties are ignoring the dots
...and just going beyond them,
...which is a bit weird.
But we've not yet
reached peak horrible.
Let's make this a C-sharp,
...and for demonstration purposes,
...let's add a natural
accidental here.
Yummy.
Now we have ties
crisscrossing each other
...and skewering these
poor accidentals.
Finally, if I drag this
G down to be an F,
...now the ties are
actually intersecting
...and obscuring the
augmentation dots too.
It's military-grade jank.
In version 4,
...let's go through
the same process.
If we add the ties,
...there are no collisions,
...and the peaks of the arcs
never collide with stave lines.
If we add augmentation dots,
...they're taken into account too.
Now, if we add those
same accidentals again,
...no collisions.
Also (and I really
love this, by the way),
...if you increase or decrease
the distance between chords,
...the ties cleverly update to
find the best possible positioning
...so the arcs don't
end up on the stave lines.
It's on a completely different
level to what we had before.
Apart from thanking Simon,
...you can thank our
engraving engineer Aaron
...for the implementation
of all this stuff.
He worked incredibly hard on it.
Another thing Aaron spent
a ton of time on was
...a new algorithm for
how beaming works,
...so that it would be
more rigorous and logical.
Many of the principles
Simon and Aaron followed
...are documented in Ted Ross' book
'The Art of Music Engraving
and Processing',
...which has long been considered the
most comprehensive text on beaming rules.
So, this is an example
of beaming in version 3.
One of the main aims of the algorithm
...is to avoid what
Ross calls "wedges",
...which occur at these intersections
...at the beginning
or end of the beam.
We also wanted to avoid
unnecessary intersections
...between stave lines and beams too,
...because they generate more
noisy objects on the page.
In version 4, you can see that
...all this noise has been removed.
This is important, because
...beaming occurs
all the time in notation.
So when dealing with full scores,
...this system clears away
hundreds, if not thousands,
...of instances of
distracting visual noise.
Then there's our notation font Leland,
...which I released a
video about last year.
We've added around 200 more symbols
...and redesigned many
of the existing ones.
If you recall, I mentioned before
...that I suspected I'd need
to revise those note flags,
...which are by far the
hardest symbols to get right.
Well, after living with
them for a few months,
...we became unhappy
with this sort of...
...humpiness you see here,
...so I created straighter,
more elegant versions instead.
Happily, a community contributor
called Nick Mazuk,
...who also contributed quite a
bit to our beaming, by the way,
...refined how the stem length
of notes are displayed
...so that these new flags
would always sit perfectly
...no matter where on
the stave they appeared.
Now, one of the toughest nuts
to crack in all engraving
...is horizontal spacing,
...which is the ultimate balancing act.
Simon had written a massive
specification for this,
...which was so complicated
...and required such
a fundamental rewrite
...we decided it was safer to
delay it until a later version.
That is, until one morning
...Simon and I noticed a
random submission coming in
...from a community
member called Michele
...who we'd never heard of before.
Turns out Michele had been following
...the work we'd done
on engraving last year,
...and had noticed all our talk about
the horizontal spacing problem,
...and just decided one day
to try his hand at it.
At first, we thought,
"Who is this person,"
"...and why does he think he
has the answer to this problem?"
But once we played around
with his submission,
...our initial perception of
him very quickly changed to
"We gotta get this guy in our team."
Michele was actually
studying a PhD in Physics
...in Vienna at the time
and, believe it or not,
...quit that PhD to come
work on Musescore.
I asked him a while ago why he
was so eager to make this change,
...and I really enjoyed his response:
Again,
...this project was just
blessed with good luck.
Now, to understand what
Michele actually did,
...let's look at the
issues with Musescore 3,
...which is that it tends to create
...far too much additional
space to everything
...and had poor systems
for achieving consistency.
Here's a classic example.
It's giving too much space
to these 30-second notes
...and incredibly inconsistent
spacing to these quarter notes.
So, even though these quarter notes
are all exactly the same duration,
...it's hard to look
at them and not feel
...an instinctive increase in tempo.
In version 4,
...everything has been rebalanced.
These 30 seconds don't
take up so much space,
...and the quarter note durations
are perfectly consistent.
In Musescore 3,
...durations were
unnecessarily lengthened
...when an accidental was added,
...again causing spacing weirdness
...where these two bars are quite
a bit larger than the others.
In Musescore 4,
...they're now all
perfectly consistent.
Here's another example from 3.
Look how much space that's taking up.
This actually highlights
one of the major reasons
...horizontal spacing is so important,
...because when you're writing
for multiple instruments,
...the measure that
has the most detail
...defines the amount of space
...all the other measures
are going to get.
And now look at version 4,
...where things are tucked in neatly.
Way more consistent with
a lot of saved space.
One of the worst horizontal
spacing problems in Musescore 3
...was how it handled tuplets.
You can see here that the
spacing is all over the place.
But after Michele's work,
...they now look like this.
You don't know how satisfying
it was for all of us
...when this fix was finally in.
There's also some really cool
collision-avoidance stuff added too.
For example, in version 3,
...look at this.
These sharps with the arpeggio line
...have really blunt
collision avoidance
...that's causing this
big ugly gap to occur.
In version 4,
...it's way smarter
...and knows how to
tuck in here nicely.
It's actually really
cool playing with this
...to observe how it figures out
...when it has enough
space to tuck things in.
Here's another example from version 3,
...where the notes are unnecessarily
...making space for this
treble clef down here.
Not so in version 4.
Apart from horizontal spacing,
...there are hundreds of other
little engraving improvements
...that would require a
whole video to go through.
But just to name a few:
Footers now have consistent padding
...so that they don't
overlap notation.
In Musescore 3,
...systems would all start
at different positions
...depending on the length
of the instrument name.
Now they all start at
the same position.
Dynamics used to be
centered to notes
...based on the width
of their bounding box,
...which is too blunt
a system that gives
...slightly off-centered-
looking results,
...mainly because
dynamics are italicized.
To fix this,
...we now recognize what's called
...the 'optical center' of dynamics,
...a smooth little definition
which we included
...in this version of Leland.
Lines at the end of a system,
...like ottava marks,
...lyrics,
...trills,
...slurs and ties
...used to overlap
the final bar line,
...which intersected nastily
with these key changes.
Now they don't.
Nested tuplets used to
intersect each other,
...and now they don't either.
And when tuplets are
part of a beamed group,
...we have more
intelligent bracketing
...that makes them
easier to recognize.
I've put a link in the
description to a post by Simon
...that lists out all the
other changes we've made.
So one last thing I
should mention is that
...as we were gradually introducing
all these improvements,
...I'd often share little updates
with their progress on Twitter.
This turned out to be
quite practically useful,
...because there were
a few occasions where
...people pointed out little details
that helped us improve things further.
And it's worth mentioning that
we're by no means finished.
There's a lot more coming down the pipe
...that's being worked on right now.
One of the petrifying
things about overhauling
...the code base with 15 years
worth of development put into it
...is that you are inevitably
going to introduce
...thousands of bugs.
On GitHub, where we track this stuff,
...Musescore 4 has almost
3,000 reported bugs,
...and that number
can easily be doubled
...if we include all the
internal testing done
...before features are pushed
to the master version.
Dealing with this number
of bugs presents
...significant
organizational problems,
...since every bug
needs investigation.
Is it well described?
Can it be reproduced reliably
...to help developers
isolate and fix it?
Is the bug out of date?
Is it really a bug, or is it
meant to be that way?
Is it a critical bug that
needs to be fixed now,
...or is it medium priority,
...or is it trivial?
If you don't stay on top of
these questions every day,
...you lose sight of
the health of your app,
...all but guaranteeing that
...critical problems get
released to the public.
Thankfully, we were again
struck with good luck,
...when about halfway
through development
...I found Dmitry, a composer
...who has a decade of experience
testing notation software.
He then brought in Borys,
...another highly
knowledgeable tester
...with a background in
music and composition.
Dmitry and Borys worked tirelessly,
...reporting, confirming,
prioritizing, and testing
...fixes for Mac, PC, and Linux,
...day after day after day.
Releasing Musescore 4 would have
been a scary prospect without them.
And by the way, since they
both live in Ukraine,
...they did this work under unimaginably
awful circumstances throughout 2022.
Now, the community also played
a massive role in testing too.
Bug-fixing is one
of those superpowers
...that comes with being
an open-source project,
...because it provides loads
of experience to users
...who can sniff out all kinds
of weird little niche issues
...and can often jump in
to help solve them too.
Apart from testing,
...another problem for us was that
Musescore 4 was going to make
...all our existing documentation
and tutorials obsolete,
...and we had to tackle
this in two ways.
First, we created a
new online manual,
...a massive task headed
up by Bradley and Peter,
...along with our longtime community
contributor Marc Sabatella,
...who's been around
since the early days.
The manual has now been opened up
...so that the rest of
the community can provide
...contributions and
translations too.
Second, we created a new
series of video tutorials,
...some targeted at existing users,
...some at new users.
Bradley and I split the production work
of all these videos down the middle.
And then we created a 'Learn'
section in the app itself
...to make them easier to find.
The most stressful part came about
...three or four months
before the release,
...when there were multiple
features still not finished
...and around 500 critical
bugs left to fix.
It was just a crazy bottleneck
period for everyone,
...a once-in-a-lifetime
release that was so big
...it just consumed everything.
And I'm pretty sure I can speak
for the team when I say that
...the main emotions
involved in releasing
...were pride, yes,
...but also a lot of relief.
It's over.
We're done.
Now, I wanted to mention one
other thing before I sign off.
A very satisfying
and wholesome feeling
...that comes with
contributing to Musescore.
I've built a lot of
software over the years.
And looking back, I can now see
...that a significant portion of my life
has been dedicated to software that,
...for one reason or
another, is now obsolete,
...with the code being
locked away forever
...so that no one can ever
see it or benefit from it.
But since Musescore is
an open-source project,
...we know that all our work
will always be available
...for others to build
upon in the future.
As long as there are users and
community members invested in it,
...it will continue to live,
and will very likely provide
...a springboard for new solutions
in the unpredictable future.
And the license we use, GPL,
...is kind of like an
open-source patent.
What we build under the GPL
...can only be reused by apps
that are also using GPL,
...which continuously
shores up the advantage
...that the Free Software movement
has over proprietary software.
So, with that in mind,
here's to all the people
...who contributed to
Musescore over the years,
...and also all the
millions of people
...who use it to create
sheet music every day.
We hope our de-Houstonification,
...which took the lives
of many criminology dogs,
...significantly de-jankifies
...your experience.